Alexander Soeters

Business Analyst/Controller and Excel & Power BI specialist with a history of working in FMCG, Consultancy, Tech and Insurance industry. I help companies improve their reporting, primarily through the use of Excel, VBA & Power BI I am fluent in English & Dutch



PERSONAL INFO

Phone: +31 6 24678311 Email: soeters@live.com

Linkedin: www.linkedin.com/in/agsoeters
Place of residence: Amsterdam, The Netherlands

SKILLS

- Excel VBA, Power BI, Power Query, Power Pivot, DAX, Basic SQL
- SAP Business Objects & ERP, Qlikview, Hyperion FM, Oracle, Azure & KPI Lake, MSSS
- Native in English & Dutch

EXPERIENCE

Mercedes-Benz Financial Services, Nieuwegein — *BI analyst a.i.*

OCTOBER 2022 - DECEMBER 2023

- Mapped the entire MB Financial Services business in order to develop and implement Power BI Dashboarding and automation improvements
- Worked as ad-hoc Risk Controller (4 months) and OPEX controller (6 months) and conducted monthly calls with management on their financials, but also data needs
- Through the use of Power Query and Power Pivot, enabled MB Portfolio and Acquisition files to run seamlessly during the close without any manual intervention, just a simple refresh
- Improved Insurance and Risk monthly close files to connect to a centralised Data-model, instead of relying on unstable links to other files
- Worked closely with the IT team in order to communicate business requirements
- Trained the controlling team on Power BI functionalities and helped them with their reporting requirements
- Gained knowledge of MS SQL Server system throughout my time at MBFS

Bol.com, Utrecht — Reporting specialist a.i.

IANUARY 2022 - SEPTEMBER 2022

- Developed a dynamic "one-click refresh" Actual and Forecast P&L. Each BU P&L is specifically tailored to the wishes of the responsible Business Unit controller. These reports are now being used by all financials within the company
- Played a key role in redesigning the entire Forecasting process and am continually improving the Vena database and P&L structure where needed
- Developed automated waterfall bridges for periodic, quarterly, and ytd reporting
- Automated monthly P&L reporting decks through the use of Excel VBA

• Built a simple "one-click" Excel to Powerpoint upload through the use of Excel VBA so that MT can get as many Actual or Budget reviews as they like in a powerpoint format

Microsoft, Amsterdam — Consulting Financial Analyst a.i.

OCTOBER 2020 - JUNE 2021

- Assisted the WE Services HQ finance and business in managing the WE P&L and Key Services Financial processes
- Developed a monthly Azure Usage file and Flash email for all WE countries using Power BI, now used worldwide within Microsoft
- Developed a monthly CSU (Account Manager performance tracker) file for all WE countries using Power BI, now used worldwide within Microsoft
- Automated outlook heatmaps for all WE countries using Excel VBA
- Managed the Spanish Subregion for paternity leave, providing Monthly Close, Outlook and Budgetary analysis & commentary
- Created a gap to target file in order to track WE progress throughout the year
- Provided Monthly outlook overviews for The Netherlands & Belgium
- Weekly Netherlands and Belgium revenue outlook

Action, Zwaagdijk HQ — Business Analyst Commercial Control a.i.

OCTOBER 2019 - MAY 2020

- Reporting of weekly sales data for the commercial control department. (I reduced the weekly sales data production time from 3 hours to 15 minutes a week through the use of Excel VBA)
- Developed a monthly Direct import analysis file in order to assist the Logistics and Controlling team. This file combined inventory inflow, stock on ship, actual and budgeted sales data. Data was sourced from SAP, Qlikview and other Excel files
- Developed a one click weekly SKU inflow file using Excel VBA
- Developed a file which measured margin impact due to product price changes
- In-store shelf change before and after analysis
- Pricing analysis per country
- FMCG strategy analysis
- Ad hoc pricing and supplier business analysis
- Assisted in transition from reporting system Qlikview to SAP Business Objects

GoldRepublic, Amsterdam — Precious Metals Financial Analyst & Manager

JANUARY 2016 - FEBRUARY 2019

- Financial and operations management of physical precious metals to retail customers
- Financial analysis & forecasting
- Wrote financial and gold related articles for DFT and investing.com and held seminars in RAI

Baker McKenzie, Amsterdam — Business Controller

MARCH 2015 - AUGUST 2015

- Implement new SAP system from Business Objects, streamline weekly reporting
- Monthly analysis to senior partners

Boston Consulting Group, Amsterdam — Business Controller

JUNE 2012 - FEBRUARY 2015

This was a new role in which I used SAP Business Objects to create the following:

- Created weekly revenue and billability analysis review for CEO and senior partners
- Provided partner group with a weekly project review analysis
- Created standardised revenue and cost analysis reports
- Created a better outlook analysis as well as a historical tracking method
- Responsible for entire monthly/quarterly/year-end performance review

Liberty Global, Amsterdam HQ — *Finance Operations Manager*

MAY 2011 - MAY 2012

- Business control and support of local financial management through business analysis
- Provided general management visibility on financial and non-financial KPI's within the UPC affiliates
- Provided monthly capex reviews

Dutchcards — Owner

JANUARY 2010 - PRESENT

• Design and sale of souvenir products to various museums and high-end stores in The Netherlands, such as Mauritshuis, Heineken Experience, Rembrandthuis, Hermitage, Waldorf Astoria and others

Heineken, Amsterdam HQ — Business controller region Western Europe

MARCH 2009 - FEBRUARY 2010

- Execution and management of the business control cycle and support local financial management in two major areas: Global Export and Duty Free, a €500 million sales per annum business
- Financial monitoring of business performance
- Key in providing implementation of SAP integration

Philips, Amsterdam HQ — Business Controller Business Unit Domestic Appliances and Water & Air Category

JUNE 2008 - FEBRUARY 2009

- Month End Closing for Business Unit Domestic Appliances
- Financial reporting to Domestic Appliances and Water & Air Management
- Analysis and forecasting of Sales for Water & Air Category

Philips, Amsterdam HQ — Assistant Controller Finance & Accounting Region Europe

JANUARY 2006 - MAY 2008

- European lead in SAP sector integration
- Month End Closing for European region
- Performed monthly balance sheet reviews (for Benelux and Russia off-shore)
- Delivery of weekly sales analysis and forecasting for management meetings

EDUCATION

Erasmus Universiteit Rotterdam — *Master of Science (MSc.) in Economics & Business* AUGUST 2004 - DECEMBER 2005

London School of Economics and Political Science — Master of Science (MSc.) in Industrial Relations and Personnel Management

SEPTEMBER 2001 - SEPTEMBER 2002

The College of William & Mary, Virginia, USA — Bachelor of Business Administration (BBA) in Finance & Bachelor of Arts (BA) in Economics

AUGUST 1997 - MAY 2000